Guide to the UCSF/Stanford Hospital Merger Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
UCSF/Stanford Hospital Merger records
1997-2000
SC0593
Stanford University. Office of the General Counsel.
133 Linear feet (102 boxes)
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are restricted 20 years from date of creation.
Biographical/Historical note
During the 1980s, both Stanford and UCSF engaged in major hospital expansion projects. Subsequent cutbacks of federal funds resulted in the disappearance of traditional profit margins despite sizeable cuts in budgets at both institutions. In 1986, California Pacific Medical Center, Stanford, and UCSF established the California Transplant Donor Network in San Francisco to eliminate competition for transplant organs. This unusual act of cooperation was followed by a meeting in 1993 of Stanford Dean David Korn with UCSF Dean Joseph Martin to discuss other areas of possible cooperation between the two medical schools.
At the 1995 meeting of the California Business Higher Education Forum, the topic of discussion was the decline in federal funding for medical research and for Medicare payments for services. UCSF Chancellor Joseph Martin and Stanford President Gerhard Casper took a walk during an intermission and agreed that the two schools ought to share more and compete less. Not long thereafter, Stanford and UCSF announced that discussions were taking place regarding collaboration with patient care programs, and the formation of other alliances between the two institutions. Both parties made it clear that the medical schools and medical faculties would remain independent.
Despite labor concerns, the Board of Regents voted in July, 1996 that the merged health care system would be a private, non-profit corporation. The Board of Regents approved the merger uniting UCSF Medical Center; UCSF Mount Zion Hospital, with Stanford Health Services, which comprises Stanford University Hospital and related clinics; and the Lucile Salter Packard Children's Hospital. UCSF Stanford Health Care (USHC) began operation in 1997.
There was a significant Increase in clinical activity in the first year of the merger, but the growth was not sustained. The merger produced a profit of $22 million in the first year. Then, largely because of administrative costs, UCSF Stanford Health Care sustained an $11 million deficit in the first quarter of the second year, and is expected to lose $60 million by the end of the second year.
The expectation that the merger would create five multi-disciplinary service lines during the first five years was not realized. The absence of an adequate information base and lack of faculty enthusiasm postponed the creation of service lines except in adult cardiology, pediatric cardiology, and pediatric neurosurgery, and the failure to integrate the transplantation and cancer programs of the two schools was a notable disappointment.
Supporters of the merger saw two distinguished faculties creating a single clinical entity, perhaps becoming the nation's premier academic health center, but this goal was not achieved. After a year and a half, the two faculties failed to come together, and in the first months of 1999 leaders of both institutions became aware of a large financial deficit. In spring of the following year, the merger was officially dissolved.
Access Terms
Hospitals; Hospitals, University.; Hospitals--California--Palo Alto.; Hospitals--Design and construction.
Collection Contents
- Records of Gerhard Casper, Accession ARCH-2000-205
  - GC/Ill additions, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Needs Action, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Unlabeled Folder with memorandums and drafts, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Unlabeled Folder with Business Plan Document, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - UCSF Stanford Demerger Decision, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Background Information Meeting, 5/30/1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Unlabeled Folder with Board of Trustees Documents, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Unlabeled Folder with NEWCO documents, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Unlabeled Folder with Stanford Legal Office Memo and Agenda, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loose Papers (Legal Office, Photocopies of Health & Safety Code), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Drafts of Principal Consolidation Documents, 10/18/1997 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - UCSF-Stanford Healthcare Documents, 10/18/1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - UCSF, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - UCSF/Stanford, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Unlabeled Folder with Planning Meeting and Regents' Items, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Unlabeled Folder with Meeting Agenda and Notes, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - UCSF, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Unlabeled Folder about Bylaws and Liability Issues, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - BoT / USHC, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Unlabeled Folder with Legal Documents and Senate Bill, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence regarding Merger, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - State Audit Bureau Report: UCSF Stanford Health Care, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mailings, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bain's Latest Draft and Bureau of State Audit Report, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Third Party Review, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Unlabeled Folder with "The $100 Million Project" and Faxes, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Status Report, 7/25/1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Assembly Bill, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Drafts, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Stanford School of Medicine FY93/94, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Stanford Health Services Board of Directors Meeting, 11/11/1996 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Records
  - Board of Directors Minutes 1
  - Board of Directors Minutes 2
  - Board of Directors Alphabetical Files 3
  - Board of Directors 4 Miscellaneous Files
  - Board of Directors Alphabetical Files Executive Committee Minutes
  - Board of Directors Alphabetical Files 2
  - Risk Management 1—Personnel Files/Dept. Binders
  - Risk Management 1—Insurance Reports and Policies
  - Risk Management 2—Miscellaneous Cases A-C
  - Chief Financial Officer 1
  - Chief Financial Officer 1–General Files
  - Chief Financial Officer 1–State Audit Files
  - Chief Financial Officer 1–State Audit Files
  - Chief Financial Officer 2–General Files M-P
  - Chief Financial Officer 2—General Files/Mt. Zion Binders
  - Chief Financial Officer 3—Presentations
  - Chief Financial Officer 3—Presentations, cont.
  - Chief Financial Officer 3—Financial Workpapers; Chief Financial Officer 3—Presentations
  - Chief Financial Officer 3—Presentations; Chief Financial Officer 3—Financial Workpapers
  - Chief Financial Officer 3—Financial Workpapers
  - Historical Benefits Information
  - Historical Benefits Information, cont.
  - Human Resources—Treva Davis' files
  - Human Resources
  - Human Resources—General Files A-K
  - Human Resources—General Files A-K, cont.
  - Human Resources—General Files L-U
  - Human Resources—General Files L-U, cont.
  - Human Resources—General Files U-Z
  - Human Resources--General Files U-Z
  - Human Resources—Resumes/Applications
  - Human Resources—Resumes/Applications. Misc File Cabinet.
  - Human Resources—Benefits Binders, CRONA
  - Human Resources—Benefits – CRONA and AFSCME.
  - Human Resources—Resumes/Applications
  - Human Resources—Resumes/Applications, cont.
  - Original box unlabeled. Reboxed into an RSB
  - General Counsel 1—Subject Files A-C #1
  - General Counsel 1—Subject Files A-C #2
  - General Counsel 1—Subject Files A-C #3
  - General Counsel 1—Subject Files C-M #1
  - General Counsel 1—Subject Files C-M #2
  - General Counsel 1—Subject Files C-M #3
  - General Counsel 1—Subject Files M-Z #1
  - General Counsel 1—Subject Files M-Z #2
  - General Counsel 1—Subject Files M-Z #3
  - General Counsel 1—Law Firms and Financial #1
  - General Counsel 1—Law Firms and Financial #2
  - General Counsel 1—Law Firms and Financial #3
  - General Counsel 2—Unwind and Government Relations #1
  - General Counsel 2—Unwind and Government Relations #2
  - General Counsel 2—Unwind and Government Relations #3
  - General Counsel 2—Litigation: Bankruptcy; Mt. Zion Closure #1
  - General Counsel 2—Litigation: Bankruptcy; Mt. Zion Closure #2
  - General Counsel—Corporate Document Binders #1
  - General Counsel—Corporate Document Binders #2
  - General Counsel—Corporate Document Binders #3
  - General Counsel—Corporate Document Binders #4
  - General Counsel—Compliance Department Binders
  - General Counsel—Compliance Department Binders, cont.
  - General Counsel—Compliance Department Binders, cont.
  - Reimbursement—Reimbursement Files and Binders
  - Miscellaneous—Admin Files – Corporate Vendor
  - Miscellaneous—Strategic Development – Govt. Relations and Marketing
  - Miscellaneous—Admin Files – Corporate Vendor, cont.
  - 11/15/00 UCSF Stanford Void A/P's
  - 11/15/00 UCSF Stanford Void A/P's, cont.
  - 11/15/00 UCSF Stanford Voids
  - 11/15/00 UCSF Stanford Misc A/P Files
  - 11/15/00 729401 5/5/98 – 730999 5/8/98
  - 11/15/00 922356 08/09/99 – 943053 10/11/99
  - 11/15/00 946997 10/25/99 – 950954 11/4/99
  - 11/15/00 942906 10/11/99 – 949855 10/29/99
  - 11/15/00 942906 8/9/99 – 934036 9/7/99
  - 11/15/00 949857 10/29/99 – 955820 11/19/99
  - 11/15/00 956336 11/22/99 – 960092 12/6/99
  - 11/15/00 961090 12/8/99 – 967548 12/30/99
  - 11/15/00 986567 2/29/00 —>
  - 11/15/00 934516 9/8/99 – 942412 10/7/99
  - 11/15/00 977127 1/31/00 – 986114 2/28/00
  - 11/15/00 968273 1/3/00 – 976050 1/27/00
  - 11/15/00 H, I, N-Q J K L O P Q PERLA TRAM MOFFITT
  - 11/15/00 UCSFHS A/P Check Registers G/L Reports 3/31. 03/10/00 – 03/31/00
  - 11/15/00 989590 3/8/00 – 999160 4/28/00
- Meeting minutes, 1997-2000; Accession ARCH-2013-032
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Meetings, 1997 Mar 19 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors Presidents Report - March 10, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Financial Presentation - October, 1997 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting - December 5, 1997 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Children Services Committee meeting - December 5, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 1)
  - Draft Resolution: Extension of LPCH License - Dec. 2, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Gregory Moser Memo - Nov. 13, 1997 - Revised Procedures for Compliance with SB 1350 (CH 927, Stats. 1997) (Box 1)
  - Sample Agenda UCSF Stanford Healthcare, Oct 9 1998 (Box 1)
  - Draft UCSF I SHC Public Access to Records Policy (Box 1)
  - Bylaws of UCSF - SHC, 1997 Sep 19 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Meetings, 1999 Jan 11 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Audit & Compliance Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Adult Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Children Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - LPCH Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Finance Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Community Relations Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Meetings, 1999 Feb 22 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - LPCH Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Adult Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Children Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Community Relations Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Finance Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Meetings, 1999 Apr 30 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - LPCH Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Adult Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Children Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Audit & Compliance Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Finance Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Meetings, June 16,1999 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Adult Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Children Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Community Relations Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Finance Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - LPCH Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Meetings, 1999 Jul 23 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - LPCH Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Audit & Compliance Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Children Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - October/August 1999 (Box 1)
  - August 26,1999 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Finance Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - August 27,1999 UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting, 1999 Oct 22 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Adult Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Children Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Meetings, December 3,1999 (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Adult Services Committee meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting (Box 1)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Miscellaneous Comm Mtgs, 1999/2000 (Box 1)
  - Compensation Committee - 1998/1999 (Box 1)
  - Credentials Committee Meetings - Jan 1999 to Aug 1999 (Box 1)
  - So Campus Operations Committee - December 22, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Nominating Committee - October 20, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Committee List dated Dec 19, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Committee List dated Mar 17, 1998 (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting - January 14, 2000 (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Audit & Compliance/Finance Committee meeting - Jan 14,2000 (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting - February 25, 2000 (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting - March 31, 2000 conf call (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Audit & Compliance/Finance Committee meeting - Feb 25, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Correspondence dated Jan 2000 and Feb 2000 (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting - March 31, 2000 conference call (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting - May 4, 2000 conference call (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting - August 1, 2000 conference call (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Board of Directors meeting - November 27, 2000 conference call (Box 2)
  - Audit Financial Statements FINAL from Arthur Andersen - March 31, 2000 (Box 2)
  - UHSC Actions by Written Consent re: Officer Appts. And Fiscal Year Change (Box 2)
  - So Campus Operations Committee - January 27, 2000 (Box 2)
  - No Campus Operations Committee - February 8, 2000 (Box 2)
  - SUH Articles of Incorporation - amended July 2, 1968 (copies) (Box 2)
  - UHSC Board of Directors Lists (Box 2)
  - SHS and Hospital Board Rosters (Box 2)
  - Board Dinner - June 20, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Isaac Stein Board Member file (Box 2)
  - Medical Center Report Articles - January 15, 1997 re: merger (Box 2)
  - Medical Center Report Special Pullout section re: merger (Box 2)
  - SHS Forum (Box 2)
  - Medical Professional Liability Insuranace Company, Inc. First Board Meeting Materials 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - UHSC Actions by Written Consent re: Pension Plan Amendment - May 29, 2002 (Box 2)
  - HS215 Forms 1999 (Box 2)
  - UCSF / Stanford Health Care Joint Finance & Audit Minutes (unofficial) - Nov 1999 - Feb 2000 (Box 2)
  - UCSF I Stanford Health Care Audit Minutes (unofficial) - Jan 1999 - Nov 1999 (Box 2)
  - UCSF I Stanford Health Care Finance Minutes (unofficial) - Feb 1999 - Oct 1999 (Box 2)
  - Board Closed Session Minutes - Jan 1998 - Nov 2000 (Box 2)
  - Executive Session Closed Session Minutes - March 1998 - Nov 1999 (Box 2)
  - Board Open Session Minutes - Jan 1997 - Aug 2000 (Box 2)
  - Executive Session Closed Session Minutes - March 1998 - Nov 1999 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanous Correspondence (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Orientation Manual - September 25, 1998 (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care official Seal (Box 2)
  - UCSF Stanford Health Care Tapes from meetings - 2 envelopes (Box 2)